X-Men: The Mutant Watch is a documentary film directed by Thomas C. Grane.
While Senator Kelly addresses a senate committee about the supposed
mutant menace, we learn about the making of the movie, X-Men.
Sen. Robert Kelly, played by Bruce Davison.
Terry Anzur, played by Terry Anzur.
Self - Director, played by Bryan Singer.
Self - 'Logan / 'Wolverine', played by Hugh Jackman.
Self - Executive Producer / Story, played by Tom DeSanto.
Self - 'Xavier', played by Patrick Stewart.
X-Men is a 2000 American superhero film  based on the Marvel Comics
superhero team created by Stan Lee and Jack Kirby.
Directed by Bryan Singer from a screenplay by David Hayter and a story by Singer and Tom DeSanto, it features an ensemble cast consisting of Patrick
Stewart, Hugh Jackman, Ian McKellen, Halle Berry, Famke Janssen, James Marsden, Bruce Davison, Rebecca Romijn, Ray Park, and Anna Paquin.
The film depicts a world where an unknown proportion of people are mutants,
possessing superhuman powers that make them distrusted by normal humans.
It focuses on mutants Wolverine and Rogue as they are brought into a conflict between two groups with radically different approaches to
bringing about the acceptance of mutant-kind: Charles Xavier's X-Men, and the Brotherhood of Mutants, led by Magneto.
Development of X-Men began as far back as 1984 with Orion Pictures, with
James Cameron and Kathryn Bigelow in discussions at one point.
20th Century Fox bought the film rights in 1994, and various scripts and film treatments were
commissioned from Andrew Kevin Walker, John Logan, Joss Whedon, and Michael Chabon.
Singer signed to direct in 1996, with further rewrites by Ed Solomon, Singer, Tom DeSanto, Christopher
McQuarrie, and Hayter, in which Beast and Nightcrawler were deleted over budget concerns from Fox.
X-Men marked the American debut for Jackman, a last-second
choice for Wolverine, cast three weeks into filming.
Filming took place from September 22, 1999, to
March 3, 2000, primarily in Toronto.
X-Men premiered at Ellis Island on July 12, 2000, and was
released in the United States on July 14.
The film received positive reviews from critics and was a box office success, grossing
$296.3 million worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2000.
Its success led to a series of films, with the first
sequel, X2, released on May 2, 2003.
Several actors reprise their roles in Marvel Cinematic Universe films, including Stewart in Doctor Strange in the Multiverse of Madness
(2022), Jackman in Deadpool & Wolverine (2024), and Stewart, McKellen, Marsden, and Romijn in Avengers: Doomsday (2026).
The film explores themes of mutant, behind the scenes, senate hearing.